[Music]
Reedman reads the Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
7 Now Jonas's group had taken a new place in the Auditorium, trading with the
new 11s so that they sat in the very front, immediately before the stage. They
were arranged ched by the original numbers, the numbers they had been given at
birth. The numbers were rarely used after the Naming. But each child knew his number, of
course. Sometimes parents used them in irritation at a child's misbehavior,
indicating that mischief made one unworthy of a name. Jonas always chuckled when he heard
a parent, exasperated, call sharply to a whining todler That's enough
23 Jonas was 19 He had been the the 19th new child born his year. It had meant
that at his Naming, he had been already standing in bright eyed soon to walk and
talk. It had given him a slight advantage the first year or two, a little more
maturity than many of his groupmates who had been born in the later months of
that year. But it evened out, as it always did, by Three. After Three, the children
progressed at much the same level, though by their first number one could always
tell who was a few months older than others in his group.
Technically, Jonas's full number was 1119 since there were other 19s of
course, in each age group. And today, now that the new 11s had been advanced this
morning, there were two 111 19s At the midday break he had exchanged smiles
with a new one, a shy female named Harriet. But the duplication was only for these few
hours. Very soon he would not be an 11 but a 12 an age would no longer matter.
He would be an adult, like his parents, though a new one and untrained
still. Asher was Four, and sat now in the row ahead of Jonas. He would receive his
Assignment fourth. Fiona 18 was on his left; on his other side sat 20 a male
named Pierre whom Jonas didn't like much.
Pierre was very serious, not much fun, and a worrior and tattletail too. "Have you
checked the rules, Jonas?" Pierre was always whispering solemnly. "I'm not sure
that's within the rules." Usually it was some foolish thing
that no one cared about— —opening his tunic if it was a day with a breeze;
taking a brief try on a friend's bicycle, just to experience the different feel of
it. The initial speech at the Ceremony of 12 was made by the Chief Elder, the
leader of the community who was elected every 10 years. The speech was much the same each
year: recollection of the time of childhood and the period of
preparation, the coming responsibilities of adult life, the profound importance of
Assignment, the seriousness of training to come. Then the Chief Elder moved ahead in her
speech. "This is the time," she began, looking directly at them, "when we acknowledge
differences. You Els have spent all your years till now learning to fit in,
to standardize your behavior, to curb any impulse that might set you apart from the
group. "But today we honor your differences. They have determined your
futures." She began to describe this year's group and its variety of
personalities, though she singled no one out by name. She mentioned that there was one
who had singular skills at caretaking, another who loved new children one with
unusual scientific aptitude a fourth for whom physical labor was an obvious
pleasure. Jonas shifted in his seat, trying to recognize each reference as one of his
groupmates. The caretaking skills were no doubt those of fion on his left; he
remembered noticing the tenderness with which she had bathed the
Old. Probably the one with scientific aptitude was Benjamin, the male who had
devised new, important equipment for the Rehabilitation Center. He heard nothing that he re
recognized as himself, Jonas. Finally the Chief Elder paid tribute to the hard work of her
committee, which had performed the observations so meticulously all year.
The Committee of Elders stood and was acknowledged by applause. Jonas noticed
Asher yawn slightly, covering his mouth politely with his
hand. Then, at last, the Chief Elder called number One to the stage, and the Assignments
began. Each announcement was lengthy a accompanied by a speech directed at the
new 12 Jonas tried to pay attention as One, smiling happily, received her
Assignment as Fish Hatchery Attendant along with the words of praise for her
childhood spent doing many volunteer hours there, and her obvious interest in
the important process of providing nourishment for the
community. Number One— —her name was meline returned, finally, amidst applause, to her
seat, wearing the new badge that designated her Fish Hatchery Attendant.
Jonas was certainly glad that that Assignment was taken; he wouldn't have
wanted it. But he gave meline a smile of congratulation. When Two, a female named
Inger, received her Assignment as birth mother Jonas remembered that his mother
had called at a job without honor. But he thought that the Committee had chosen
well. Inger was a nice girl though somewhat lazy, and her body was strong.
She would enjoy the three years of being pampered that would follow her brief
training; she would give birth easily and well; and the task of Laborer that would
follow would use her strength, keep her healthy, and impose
self-discipline. Inger was smiling when she resumed her seat birth mother was an
important job, if lacking in prestige. Jonas noticed that Asher looked
nervous. He kept turning his head and glancing back at Jonas until the group
leader had to give him a silent chastisement, a motion to sit still and face
forward. Three, Isaac, was given an Assignment as Instructor of Sixes, which
obviously pleased him and was welld deserved. Now there were three
Assignments gone, none of them ones that Jonas would have liked— —not that he could have been a
birth mother anyways he realized with amusement. He tried to sort through the
list in his mind, the possible Assignments that remained there were so
many he gave it up; and anyway, now it was Asher's turn. He paid strict attention as
his friend went over to the stage and stood self-consciously beside the Chief
Elder. "All of us in the community know and enjoy Asher," the Chief Elder began.
Asher grinned and scratched one leg with the other foot. The audience chuckled
softly. "When the committee began to consider Asher's Assignment," she went on,
"there were some possibilities that were immediately discarded. Some that would clearly not
have been right for Asher. "For example," she said, smiling, "we did not consider for an instant
designating Asher an Instructor of Threes." The audience howled with laughter.
Asher laughed, too, looking sheepish but pleased at the special attention. The
Instructors of Threes were in charge of the acquisition of correct
language. "In fact," the Chief Elder continued, chuckling a little herself, "we
even gave a little thought to some retroactive chastisement for the one who
had been Ash Instructor of thre so long ago. At the meeting where Asher was
discussed, we retold many of the stories that we all remembered from his days of language
acquisition. "Especially," she said, chuckling, "the difference between snack
and smack. Remember, Asher?" Asher nodded ruly and the audience laughed aloud.
Jonas did, too. He remembered, though he had been only a Three at the time
himself. The punishment used for small children was a regulated system of
smacks with a discipline wand: a thin, flexible weapon that stung painfully
when it was wielded. The Child Care specialists were trained very carefully
in the discipline methods: a quick smack across the hands for a bit of minor
misbehavior; three sharper smacks on the bare legs for a second defense Poor
Asher, who always talked too fast in mixed up words, even as a
toddler. As a Three, eager for his juice and crackers at snack time he he one day
said "smack" instead of "snack" as he stood waiting in line for the morning treat.
Jonas remembered it clearly. He could still see little Asher, wiggling with
impatience in the line. He remembered the cheerful voice call out, "I want my
smack!" The other Threes, including Jonas, had laughed nervously. "Snack!" they
corrected. "You mean snack, Asher!" But the mistake had been made. And precision of
language was one of the most important tasks of small children.
Asher had asked for a smack. The discipline wand, in the hand of
the child care worker, whistled as it came down across Asher's hands. Asher
whimpered, cringed, and corrected himself instantly. "Snack," he
whispered. But the next morning he had done it again. And again the following
week. He couldn't seem to stop, though for each laps the disciplined wand came
again, escalating to a series of painful lashes that left marks on Asher's legs.
Eventually, for a period of time, Asher stopped talking altogether, when he was a
Three. "For a while," the Chief Elder said, relating the story, "we had a silent Asher!
But he learned." She turned to him with a smile. "When he began to talk again, it was
with greater precision. And now his lapses are very few. His corrections and
apologies are very prompt. And his good humor is unfailing." The audience murmured in
agreement. Asher's cheerful disposition was well known throughout the community.
"Asher." She lifted her voice to make the official announcement. "We have given you the
Assignment of Assistant Director of Recreation." She clipped on his new badge
as he stood beside her, beaming. Then he turned and left the stage as the
audience cheered. When he had taken his seat again, the Chief Elder looked down
at him and said the words that she had said now four times, and would say to
each new 12 Somehow she gave it special meaning for each of them.
"Asher," she said, "thank you for your childhood." The Assignments continued, and
Jonas watched and listened, relieved now by the wonderful Assignment his best
friend had been given. But he was more and more apprehensive as his own
approached. Now the new Twelves in the row ahead had all received their badges.
They were fingering them as they sat, and Jonas knew that each one was thinking
about the training that lay ahead. For some— —one studious male had been selected
as Doctor, a female as Engineer, and another for Law and Justice— —it would be
years of hard work and study. Others, like Laborers and birth mothers would have a much shorter
training period 18 Fiona, on his left, was called. Jonas knew she must be nervous,
but Fiona was a calm female. She had been sitting quietly, serenely, throughout the
Ceremony. Even the applause, though enthusiastic, seemed serene when Fiona
was given the important Assignment of Caretaker of the Old. It was perfect for
such a sensitive, gentle girl, and her smile was satisfied and pleased when she
took her seat beside him again. Jonas prepared himself to walk to
the stage when the applause ended and the Chief Elder picked up the next
folder and looked down to the group to call forward the next new
12 He was calm now that his turn had come. He took a deep breath and smoothed
his hair with his hand 20 he heard her voice say clearly.
"Pierre." She skipped me, Jonas thought, stunned. Had he heard wrong?
No. There was a sudden hush in the crowd, and he knew that the entire community
realized I that the Chief Elder had moved from 18 to 20 leaving a
gap. On his right, Pierre, with a startled look, rose from his seat and moved to the
stage. A mistake. She made a mistake. But Jonas knew, even as he had
the thought, that she hadn't. The Chief Elder made no mistakes. Not at the Ceremony of
12 He felt dizzy, and couldn't focus his attention. He didn't didn't hear what
Assignment Pierre received was only dimly aware of the applause that the boy
returned, wearing his new badge. Then 21 22 The numbers continued in order Jonah
sat, dazed, as they moved into the 30s and then the 40s nearing the
end. Each time, at each announcement, his heart jumped for a moment, and he thought
wild thoughts. Perhaps now she would call his name. Could he have forgotten his own
number? No. He had always been 19 He was sitting in the seat marked
19 But she had skipped him. He saw the others in his group
glance at him, embarrassed, and then avert their eyes quickly. He saw a worried look
on the face of his group leader. He hunched his shoulders and
tried to make himself smaller in the seat. He wanted to disappear, to fade away,
not to exist. He didn't dare to turn and find his parents in the crowd. He
couldn't bear to see their faces darkened with shame. Jonas bowed his head and searched
through his mind. What had he done wrong
[Music]